Mikel Egaña Aranguren, Ph.D.

Linked Data Expert Email: mikel.egana.aranguren@gmail.com
Eccenca GmbH Homepage: https://mikel-egana-aranguren.github.io

Short Bio

I am a seasoned Linked Data expert, with hands-on experience in the design and development of data integration solutions, from ontology engineering to mapping of data sources to Knowledge Graphs. I started my career in an academic setting, applying Semantic Web technologies (RDF, SPARQL, OWL, SHACL) to the problem of data integration in the Life Sciences. As I moved from academia to the private sector, I have been applying the same technologies to other domains like Government Open Data and Enterprise Data. I have worked in different countries and participated in international projects.

Even though I have mainly worked as an arquitect of Linked Data systems, I also enjoy working with very technical problems. I am fluent in Java and comfortable using Unix systems and distributed version control systems like Git.

Being a biologist by training, I started my career as a bioinformatician. Therefore, I have also done some Bioinformatics work like analysing Metagenomics data.

Education

2009	Ph.D. Computer Science, University of Manchester, UK
2005	M.Sc. Bioinformatics, University of Manchester, UK
2003	B.Sc. Biology, University of Basque Country, Spain
2002	Invited student Evolutionary Ecology at Canterbury Christ Church University
	College, UK
2002	Erasmus student Environmental Biology at Canterbury Christ Church University
	College, UK

Employment

2018/12/02 - Present	Linked Data Expert Eccenca GmbH
	Linked Data solutions for the Enterprise
2018/10/01 - 2018/12/02	Bioinformatics technician Biocruces Bizkaia
	Data infrastructure development, Bioinformatics analyses
2016/01/14 - 2018/09/30	Analyst, Torres Quevedo fellow Eurohelp Consulting
	Design and development of Linked Open Data solutions
2015/04/27 - 2016/01/14	Analyst Eurohelp Consulting
	Design and development of Linked Open Data solutions

Freelance positions

2018/10/15 - 2018/12/02 Freelance Cognizone, Belgium
Ontology Engineering

2018/05/01 - 2018/07/31 Freelance University of Murcia
Preparation of public tender in project Hercules
(Federated Linked Open Data for universities)

Freelance Intellimedis, Luxembourg
Ontology Engineering

Research positions

2014/04/01 - 2015/03/31	Post-doc researcher (80% FTE) Genomic Resources Group, UPV/EHU
	Metagenomics and Life Sciences Semantic Web
2011/02/14 - 2014/02/14	Post-doc researcher, Marie Curie Cofund fellow
	Ontology Engineering Group (Computer Science);
	Biological Informatics Group (CBGP), UPM, Spain
	Ontology Engineering and Life Sciences Semantic Web
2010/12/01 - 2011/02/01	Researcher OGO project, UM, Spain
	Orthologous Genes Ontology
2006/05/01 - 2006/10/1	Pre-doc researcher, Marie Curie EST fellow
	Computational Biology group, VIB, Belgium
	Cell Cycle Ontology and Ontology Design Patterns

Research visits

2005/09/01 - 2005/10/01 European Bioinformatics Institute (EBI), funded by the Network of Excellence on Semantic Interoperability and Data Mining in Biomedicine (EU)

Funding obtained

2018-2020 (2 years)	Declined Bioinformatics Technician. Instituto de Salud Carlos III. CA18/00021
2016-2018 (3 years)	Torres Quevedo (Spain). 35% of salary at Eurohelp Consulting. PTQ-14-07198
2011-2014 (3 years)	Marie Curie Cofund (EU). UNITE 246565
2006 (5 months)	Marie Curie EST (EU). MEST-CT-2004-414632
2005 (One payment)	EPSRC (UK): Ph.D. fees
2005 - 2008 (3 years)	University of Manchester (UK): Ph.D. maintenance allowance
2002 (5 months)	Erasmus (EU)

Participation in funded projects

2018	Servicios Directorio Linked Open Data.
	EJIE (Sociedad Informática del Gobierno Vasco). (70.000 EUR).
2017 - 2018	SOLDAGE (Semantic Open Linked DAta GEnerator). HAZITEK, Gobierno Vasco.
	FAIR data generator (150.000 EUR).
2016 - 2017	Servicios Open Linked Data. EJIE (Sociedad Informática del Gobierno Vasco).
	Linked Data implementation of Open Data Euskadi (90.000 EUR).
2016 - 2020	REPLICATE. Renaissance of Places with Innovative Citizenship And
	TEchnology (Project 691735), EU. Linked Open Data in Smart Cities
	(http://replicate-project.eu/).
	(Consortium: 24M EUR; Eurohelp: 300.000 EUR).
2015 - 2017	Linking Open Domains, Plataforma para la generación de datos enlazados
	(LODGen) (TSI-100105-2015-0012). Ministerio de Industria, Energia y Turismo (Spain),
	Accin Estratgica Economa y Sociedad Digital (AEESD) 1/2015.
	Linked Open Data pipeline (40.000 EUR).
2015 - 2016	Enlazando Gipuzkoa con el Mundo (ENGIMU). Gipuzkoako Foru Aldundia,
	Gipuzkoa IKT: Innovación digital Empresas (Spain).
	Linked Open Data pipeline (40.000 EUR).

Publications

Refereed Journal Articles

2015	Aranguren, M. E. and Wilkinson, M. D. (2015). Enhanced reproducibility of SADI Web service workflows with Galaxy and Docker. <i>GigaScience</i> , 4(59)
2015	Pawluczyk, M., Weiss, J., Links, M. G., Aranguren, M. E., Wilkinson, M. D., and Egea-Cortines, M. (2015). Quantitative evaluation of bias in PCR amplification and Next Generation Sequencing derived from metabarcoding samples. <i>Analytical and Bioanalytical Chemistry</i> , 407(7):1841–1848
2014	González, A. R., Callahan, A., Toledo, J. C., García, A., Aranguren, M. E., Dumontier, M., and Wilkinson, M. D. (2014a). Automatically exposing OpenLifeData via SADI semantic Web Services. <i>Journal of Biomedical Semantics</i> , 5(1):46+
2014	Aranguren, M. E., González, A. R., and Wilkinson, M. D. (2014). Executing SADI services in Galaxy. <i>Journal of Biomedical Semantics</i> , 5(1):42+
2014	José Antonio Miñarro Giménez, Mikel Egaña Aranguren, Boris Villazón Terrazas, and Jesualdo Tomás Fernández Breis (2014). Translational research combining orthologous genes and human diseases with the OGOLOD dataset. Semantic Web Journal, 5(2):145–149

- 2014 Mikel Egaña Aranguren, Jesualdo Tomás Fernández Breis, and Michel Dumontier (2014). Special issue on Linked Data for Health Care and the Life Sciences. Semantic Web Journal, 5(2):99–100
- Duque-Ramos, A., Fernández-Breis, J. T., Iniesta, M., Dumontier, M., Egaña Aranguren, M., Schulz, S., Aussenac-Gilles, N., and Stevens, R. (2013). Evaluation of the OQuaRE framework for ontology quality. *Expert Systems with Applications*, 40(7):2696–2703
- Egaña Aranguren, M., Fernández-Breis, J. T., Antezana, E., Mungall, C., Rodríguez González, A., and Wilkinson, M. D. (2013). OPPL-Galaxy, a Galaxy tool for enhancing ontology exploitation as part of bioinformatics workflows. *Journal of biomedical semantics*, 4(1):2
- Minarro-Gimenez, J., Egana-Aranguren, M., Villazon-Terrazas, B., and Fernandez-Breis, J. (2012). Publishing Orthology and Diseases Information in the Linked Open Data Cloud. *Current Bioinformatics*, 7(3):255–266
- 2011 Mironov, V., Antezana, E., Egaña, M., Blondé, W., De Baets, B., Kuiper, M., and Stevens, R. (2011). Flexibility and utility of the Cell Cycle Ontology. *Applied Ontology*, 6(3):247–261
- Miñarro-Gimenez, J., Aranguren, M., Béjar, R., Fernández-Breis, J., and Madrid, M. (2011). Semantic integration of information about orthologs and diseases: The OGO system. *Journal of biomedical informatics*, 44:1020–1031
- Antezana, E., Egaña, M., Blondé, W., Illarramendi, A., Bilbao, I., De Baets, B., Stevens, R., Mironov, V., and Kuiper, M. (2009b). The Cell Cycle Ontology: an application ontology for the representation and integrated analysis of the cell cycle process. *Genome Biol*, 10(5):R58
- 2009 Antezana, E., Blondé, W., Egaña, M., Rutherford, A., Stevens, R., De Baets, B., Mironov, V., and Kuiper, M. (2009a). BioGateway: a semantic systems biology tool for the life sciences. *BMC bioinformatics*, 10(Suppl 10):S11
- Egaña Aranguren, M., Wroe, C., Goble, C., and Stevens, R. (2008). In situ migration of handcrafted ontologies to reason-able forms. Data & Knowledge Engineering, 66(1):147–162
- Aranguren, M., Antezana, E., Kuiper, M., and Stevens, R. (2008a). Ontology Design Patterns for bio-ontologies: a case study on the Cell Cycle Ontology. *BMC bioinformatics*, 9(Suppl 5):S1
- 2008 Antezana, E., Egaña, M., De Baets, B., Kuiper, M., and Mironov, V. (2008b). ONTO-PERL: an API for supporting the development and analysis of bio-ontologies. *Bioinformatics*, 24(6):885

- Stevens, R., Egaña Aranguren, M., Wolstencroft, K., Sattler, U., Drummond, N., Horridge, M., and Rector, A. (2007). Using OWL to model biological knowledge. *International Journal of Human-Computer Studies*, 65(7):583–594
- Aranguren, M., Bechhofer, S., Lord, P., Sattler, U., and Stevens, R. (2007). Understanding and using the meaning of statements in a bio-ontology: recasting the Gene Ontology in OWL. *BMC bioinformatics*, 8(1):57

Book Chapters

Aranguren, M., Stevens, R., Antezana, E., Fernández-Breis, J.T., Kuiper, M., and Mironov, V. (2010). Technologies and Best Practices for Building Bio-Ontologies. In *Knowledge-Based Bioinformatics*, volume Gil Alterovitz and Marco Ramoni (Eds.), pages 67–86. Wiley Online Library

Books

2010 Aranguren, M. (2010). Role and application of ODPs in bio-ontologies. Lambert Academic Publishing

Conference Proceedings

- González, A. R., Romero, M. M., Aranguren, M. E., and Wilkinson, M. D. (2014b). Nanopublishing clinical diagnoses: tracking diagnostic knowledge base content and utilization. In 27th International Symposium on Computer-Based Medical Systems (CBMS), pages 335–340
- Iglesias, A. R., Aranguren, M. E., González, A. R., and Wilkinson, M. D. (2013). Plant Pathogen Interactions Ontology (PPIO). In Rojas, I. and Guzman, F. M. O., editors, *IWBBIO*, pages 695–702. Copicentro Editorial
- Aranguren, M., Fernández-Breis, J., and Antezana, E. (2011). OPPL-Galaxy: enhancing ontology exploitation in galaxy with OPPL. In *Proceedings of the 4th International Workshop on Semantic Web Applications and Tools for the Life Sciences*, pages 12–19. ACM
- 2010 Miñarro-Giménez, J., Aranguren, M., García-Sánchez, F., and Fernández-Breis, J. (2010). A semantic query interface for the OGO platform. In *Information Technology in Bio-and Medical Informatics*, *ITBAM 2010*, pages 128–142. Springer

Egaña, M., Rector, A., Stevens, R., and Antezana, E. (2008). Applying ontology design patterns in bio-ontologies. In Gangemi, A. and Euzenat, J., editors, *Knowledge Engineering: Practice and Patterns*, volume 5268 of *Lecture Notes in Computer Science*, pages 7–16. Springer Berlin Heidelberg

Preprints, Workshop Proceedings and other publications

2015	Aranguren, M. E. (2015). Merging OpenLifeData with SADI services using Galaxy and Docker (DOI 10.1101/013615). <i>BioRxiv</i> , Cold Spring Harbor Labs
2012	Horridge, M., Aranguren, M., Mortensen, J., Musen, M., and Noy, N. (2012). Ontology Design Pattern Language Expressivity Requirements. In WOP (Co-located with ISWC), Boston, USA
2012	Gimenez, J., Aranguren, M., and Tomas, J. (2012). NCBO-Galaxy: bridging the BioPortal web services and the Galaxy platform. In <i>ICBO</i> , <i>Graz</i> , <i>Austria</i>
2009	Fernandez-Breis, J., Aranguren, M., and Stevens, R. (2009). A quality evaluation framework for bio-ontologies. In <i>ICBO</i> , <i>Buffalo</i> , <i>USA</i>
2009	Aranguren, M., Stevens, R., and Antezana, E. (2008b). Transforming the Axiomisation of Ontologies: The Ontology Pre-Processor Language. In <i>OWL Experiences and Directions (OWLEd)</i> , Washington DC, USA
2008	Iannone, L., Egana, M., Rector, A., and Stevens, R. (2008). Augmenting the expressivity of the ontology pre-processor language. In <i>OWL Experiences and Directions</i> (OWLEd), co-located with ISWC, Karlsruhe, Germany
2008	Antezana, E., Blondé, W., Egana, M., Rutherford, A., Stevens, R., De Baets, B., Mironov, V., and Kuiper, M. (2008a). Structuring the life science resourceome for semantic systems biology: lessons from the BioGateway Project. In <i>Proceedings of the Workshop on Semantic Web Applications and Tools for Life Sciences (SWAT4LS): November 28, 2008; Edinburgh, United Kingdom</i>
2012	Marshall, M., Boyce, R., Deus, H., Zhao, J., Willighagen, E., Samwald, M., Pichler, E., Hajagos, J., Aranguren, M., Miller, M., Prudhommeaux, E., Dumontier, M., and Stephens, S. (2012). Health Care and Life Science (HCLS) Linked Data Guide (http://www.w3.org/2001/sw/hcls/notes/hcls-rdf-guide/)
2007	Aranguren, M. (2007). ¿Qué puede hacer la web semántica por la biología? In $BioGaia~7$
2003	Aranguren, M. (2003). Software libre (GNU/linux) para biólogos. In $BioGaia\ 3$

Invited Talks

2016	Los Datos Enlazados y la Web Semántica. Tikitalka, VE Interactive, Spain
2014	Building reasonable biomedical ontologies for a Life Sciences Semantic Web. 3S (Systems, Synthetic, and Semantic) Biology summer school. CIBIO (Centre for Integrative Biology), University of Trento, Italy
2011	Linked Data for Functional Genomics. NTNU, Trondheim, Norway
2010	Aplicación de la Web Semántica en Biología Molecular. Universidad de Deusto, Facultad de Ingeniería, Spain
2008	Aplicación de la Web Semántica en Bioinformática. UM, Facultad de Informática, Spain
2004	Métodos y resultados actuales en Bioinformática: know-how y know-what de las redes tecnocientíficas en Bioinformática. EHU, Facultad de Filosofía, Spain

Teaching Experience

1	
2017	Life Sciences Semantic Web. MSc Bioinformatics, UM. Spanish
2016	Life Sciences Semantic Web. MSc Bioinformatics, UM. Spanish
2016	Linked Open Data tutorial. EJIE. Spanish
2015	Linked Open Data tutorial. IZFE (Informatika Zerbitzuen Foru Elkartea, Gipuzkoa). Spanish
2015	Life Sciences Semantic Web. MSc Bioinformatics, UM. Spanish
2014	Semantic biology tutorial: Use of Semantic Web resources for knowledge discovery. 3S (Systems, Synthetic, and Semantic) Biology summer school. CIBIO (Centre for Integrative Biology), University of Trento, Italy. English
2014	Galaxy tutorial. Erasmus mundus MSc in Marine Environment and resources, UPV-EHU. English
2014	Life Sciences Semantic Web. MSc Bioinformatics, UM. Spanish
2013	Introductory talk on bioinformatics for high school students visiting the CBGP. Spanish
2013	Galaxy tutorials at CBGP. English and spanish
2013	Life Sciences Linked Data. MSc Bioinformatics, UM. Spanish

2012	OWL, as part of ATHENS course (UPM). English
2012	OWL, as part of ATHENS course (UPM). English
2011	Populous tutorial at SWAT4LS (London, UK), English
2011	OWL, as part of ATHENS course (UPM). English
2011	Web Ontology Language (OWL), as part of Artificial Intelligence MSc (UPM). English
2011	OWL/Description Logics, as part of the Artificial Intelligence course (UPM). Spanish
2005- 2008	OWL tutorials for biologists (University of Manchester, UK). English

Ph.D. panels

2016	Alejandro Rodríguez Iglesias, "FAIR approaches applied to unraveling plant-pathogen interactions data and RNA processing evolution", UPM, Spain
2013	Meifania Monica Chen, "Lipoprotein Ontology: A Formal Representation of Lipoproteins", Curtin University. Australia
2012	Jose Antonio Miñarro-Giménez, "Entorno para la gestión semántica de información biomédica en investigación traslacional". UM, Spain
2011	Doris Mejía Ávila, "Estrategia de interoperabilidad semántica en el contexto de integración de conocimiento geográfico y ambiental. Caso de aplicación: Biodiversity Ontology". UPM, Spain

Student supervision

2017	Denis Mishel Uchuari, internship at Eurohelp, Bachelor's Degree in Computer Engineering in Management and Information Systems. UPV/EHU, Spain
2015	Salvador Alonso Martínez, "Imagen Docker para pipelines de Metagenómica", Bioinformatics MSc project. UM, Spain

Service

2017	Chapter review "Integrating Biological Data using Semantic Web Technology" in "Evolutionary Genomics. Computational and statistical methods", 3rd edition, Springer.
2017	Program Committee Member at Semantic Web Solutions for Large-Scale Biomedical Data Analytics (SeWeBMeDA 2017)
2015	Program Committee Member at Linked Data workshop (CAEPIA 2015)
2015	Reviewer for BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making
2013	Special issue editor for Semantic Web Journal (SWJ): Special issue on Linked Data for Health Care and the Life Sciences
2013	Reviewer for PeerJ
2013	Reviewer for Data and Knowledge Engineering (DKE)
2012	Program Committee Member at Managing Interoperability and compleXity in Health Systems. In conjunction with the ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management
2012	Program Committee Member at Joint Workshop on Semantic Technologies Applied to Biomedical Informatics and Individualized Medicine (SATBI + SWIM 2012). In conjunction with International Semantic Web Conference (ISWC)
2012	Reviewer for BMC Bioinformatics
2012	Reviewer for Journal of Biomedical Informatics (JBI)
2012	Reviewer for Computational and Mathematical Methods in Medicine (CMMM)
2012	Reviewer for Journal of Medical Systems (JOMS)
2012	Reviewer for Journal of Biomedical Semantics (JBS)
2011	Program Committee Member at Managing Interoperability and compleXity in Health Systems. In conjunction with the ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management
2011	Program Committee Member at Knowledge Capture (K-CAP)
2011	Program Committee Member at Semantic Applied Technologies on Biomedical Informatics (SATBI 2011). In conjunction with the ACM International Conference on Bioinformatics and Computational Biology
2011	Reviewer for Semantic Web Journal (SWJ)
2011	Reviewer for Journal of Research and Practice in Information Technology (JRPIT)

2008 Program Committee Member at ONTORACT

Technical skills

Semantic Web and Linked (Open) Data (Advanced): RDF, RDFS, SPARQL, OWL, SWRL, SHACL, JSON-LD, RDFa, OWL API, RDFLib, ONTO-PERL, Jena, RDF4J, Virtuoso, Stardog, Blazegraph, Apache Marmotta, GraphDB, Pubby, Protégé and Protégé server, TopBraid composer, CKAN, D2RQ, RML.io, R2RML, Open Refine, Grafter

Programming languages (Medium): Java, Perl, Python

Programming languages (Basic): Clojure, JavaScript, JSP, Bash, Groovy

Markup languages (Basic): XML, XSLT, HTML

UNIX systems (Medium): GNU/Linux (Debian, Ubuntu, CentOS, Red Hat)

Markup languages (Medium): XML, HTML 5, CSS, \LaTeX 2 ε , MarkDown

Web Services (Basic): SADI framework, NCBO services

Web (Basic): Galaxy (Bioinformatics workflows), Apache, Nginx, Tomcat, Jetty, lighttp, Solr/Lucene, Wordpress, Drupal, Jekyll, NodeJS, Spring-MVC

Software development (Basic): Maven, Ant, Leiningen, SCons, Eclipse, Subversion, Mercurial, Git (GitHub, GitLab), Travis CI, Jenkins, CodeCov

Project management (Basic): Jira, Trac, Scrum, GitHub projects

SQL and NoSQL Databases (Basic): MySQL, PostgreSQL, Neo4j, MongoDB

Documentation systems (Basic): Sphinx

File based data storage (Basic): HDF5, YAML, JSON

Statistical analysis (Basic): R

Cloud computing (Basic): Amazon EC2

Virtualisation (Basic): Docker, Virtual Box

Learning experience

2017	Predictive modelling. 20 hours course at Tecnalia
2003	Microsoft Visual Basic. 20 hours course at UPV/EHU
2003	Occupational hazards prevention, 30 hours course at UPV/EHU

2003	UNIX. 24 hours course at UPV/EHU
2002	ISO 9001:2000. 30 hours course at UPV/EHU
2002	XML. 16 hours course at University of Deusto
1998	Environmental sciences (Ekoeskola). 65 hours course at Erreka Ecologist Platform

Other merits

ANECA certificate: Ayudante Doctor

Member of Open Knowledge Foundation Spain (OKFN-ES) and Basque Association of Biologists (COBE)

Former member of the W3C Semantic Web Health Care and Life Sciences Interest Group and the Spanish Association of Linked Data (AELID)

Useful profiles

LinkedIn: http://es.linkedin.com/in/mikeleganaaranguren

GitLab: https://gitlab.com/mikel-egana-aranguren

GitHub: http://github.com/mikel-egana-aranguren

Google Scholar: http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=JsMMKnoAAAAJ

Scopus: http://www.scopus.com/authid/detail.url?authorId=16038705500

ResearchGate: http://www.researchgate.net/profile/Mikel_Egana

ORCID: http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8081-1839

ResearcherID: http://www.researcherid.com/rid/K-6878-2014

Last updated: November 29, 2018